Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1841-1891 and undated
  - Manuscript Prose, 1852-1891 and undated
    - Autobiographical Manuscripts
      - "(Elan E. Kelsey) Feb. 24— 1865 Eugene Kelsey" (Volume 130)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side of a sheet of ruled paper, 10 x 8 inches; about thirty-one lines. Notes on Eugene Kelsey, a soldier whom Whitman visited in the Armory Square Hospital, and on Kelsey's seven brothers and one brother-in-law, all but one of whom served in the Federal Army.
      - "How I get around at 60 and take notes. (No. 1 )" (Volume 123)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, signed, written in black ink, with instructions to the printer in red ink, on eleven sheets of paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; 259 lines. Whitman used blue pencil to number the pages and to write the words "first article" on the verso of each sheet. Bound in an octavo volume, full red morocco. The copy for the first of a series of six articles sent by Whitman to the Critic in 1881-1882; this article was pub lished in the issue dated January 29, 1881. Bookplate: A. Edward Newton.
      - "In the Revolution, a squad of British cavalrey [sic], on a raid" (Volume 113)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of ruled paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; twenty-nine lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half orange morocco. Anecdotes dealing with Whitman's grandfather, Kell Van Velsor, and with his Grandmother Whitman, during the Revolutionary War.
      - "Isaac Joseph Stephen Jesse (my grandfather) sons of Nehemiah Whitman" "Hannah Brush, (my grandmother Whitman) had only one brother" "1873. Nov. 20. Camden" "Oct. 29. '62— Brooklyn Portland avenue" (Volume 120)
        Description from Frey: Four autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on four sheets of paper, about 5x5 inches, one side only; about fifty-five lines in all. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, undyed morocco back. Notes on various relatives, especially Hannah Brush, a grandmother, and Mrs. Sarah Mead, his mother's aunt. With two clippings on the latter.
      - "June 2, '74 visited Dr. Grier again today" (Volume 122)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; twenty-three lines. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, brown morocco back. Notes on the opinion of the poet's physical condition held by his new Philadelphia doctor. With: an autograph letter, signed, from Dr. William Drinkard of Washington to Dr. Matthew Grier, July 24, 1873, three pages, endorsed by Whitman on the fourth page, a description of Whitman's condition and of the treatment earlier given him in Washington; three prescriptions by Dr. Grier, the first a copy in Whitman's hand, for medicines and the use of a galvanic battery.
      - "July 3 1st 1852—Mr. Scofield owes W. W. for eleven days work" (Box 20)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on the inside of a notebook cover, about 12 x 7 inches; eight lines, with several columns of figures. The words "Jefferson Whitman Writing Book" are written at the top of the page in ink. Mounted and framed. Business memoranda, written by Whitman while employed as a contracting house-builder.
      - "Mother's family lived only two or three miles from West Hills" (Volume 128)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of ruled paper, about 12 x 7 inches. Recto: forty-two lines, revised in ink and pencil. Verso: "tomb stones; for on the old hill, at the native place"; thirty-seven lines, fair copy. Bound in a folio volume, half blue morocco. An account of Whitman's mother's family, written in 1850 and later augmented, with a portion of a similar account of his father's family.
      - "My house and lot 328 Mickle street Camden New Jersey" (Volume 133)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in purple pencil on one sheet of paper, about 11x8 inches, one side only; sixty-seven lines. Bound in a small folio volume, marbled covers, half brown morocco. A portion of an early draft of Whitman's will, bequeathing the bulk of his estate to his epileptic brother Edward. With a newspaper clipping, "The Whitman Centennial," by Christopher Morley. Bookplate: A. Edward Newton.
      - "Nov. 23rd. 62 Portland av. Jesse Whitman the youngest of the children" (Volume 104)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches; thirty-nine lines. Bound in a duodecimo volume, half white pigskin. Notes on his uncles and on his father as carpenter and contractor. On the verso of the second sheet Whitman has made a five-line note of an appointment with Vedder at the Brother Jonathan office.
      - "Nov: 26 1880 R Worthington 770 Broadway New York" (Volume 131)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, signed, written in purple ink on two sheets of paper, about 9x8 inches, one side only; sixty lines, fair copy. Laid in a small folio volume, marbled covers, half black morocco. Whitman's statement of his difficulties with the pirate Worthington and a request for action to be taken against him (A. E. Newton, A Magnificent Farce, pages 152-153). Bookplate: A. Edward Newton. With an inscription by Newton.
      - Progenitors (Volume 104a)
        Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on four pages of paper, about 6x4 inches. Notes on 3 generations of his mother's family.
      - "? Specimen Days" (Volume 121)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of paper, about 8x5 inches; thirteen lines, with heading in pencil. Verso: an autograph letter, signed, from James M. Scovel to Walt Whitman, October 15, 1883. Bound in an octavo volume, half green morocco. Reflections on the influence of his father and mother, intended as an additional item for a new and larger edition of Specimen Days (Diary in Canada, page 66). Scovel's letter expresses a wish on the part of several physicians to see the "smiling light" of Whitman's face.
      - "Walter Whitman married Louisa Van Velsor June 8, 1816" (Volume 129)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of ruled paper, about 12 x 7 inches. Recto: thirty-two lines. Verso: "is rougher than it was on Michigan or Huron"; thirty-nine lines. Bound in a small folio volume, half green morocco. A list of the names and birth dates of the members of Whitman's family; a newspaper clipping on the death of Walter Whitman is pasted on the page. The fragment on verso is a portion of the diary of Whitman's trip from New Orleans, beginning with the journey on the Great Lakes and ending with the return to Brooklyn (Uncollected Poetry and Prose, 11, 78-79).
    - Whitman on His Own Writings
      - "'81 'Leaves of Grass' finished" (Volume 110)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in blue ink on one sheet of gray paper, about 9x6 inches, one side only; twenty-two lines, revised in black ink. Bound in a quarto volume, half green morocco. A diary jotting surveying his part in the preparation of the 1881-1882 edition for publication (Diary in Canada, pages 60-61). With two contemporary newspaper clippings describing incidents of Whitman's visit to Boston in 1881.
      - "All others have adhered to the principle, and shown it" (Volume 109)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 9x6 inches, one side only; nineteen lines. Bound in a small quarto volume, half green morocco. Two jottings, on his democratic attitude as a poet and on the difference between the foreign and the American theory of the rights of humanity (Camden Edition, vi, 36-37).
      - "And so I have put those completed poems in permanent type form" (Volume 108)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in blue ink on one sheet of gray paper, about 7x6 inches, one side only; seventeen lines, revised, with a note, "run in," in red ink at the beginning. Bound in a small quarto volume, boards. A fragment intended for a volume of Whitman's prose (Diary in Canada, pages 61-62).
      - "CURRENT CRITICISM" (Volume 127)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on two sheets of ruled paper, one side only, about 5x7 inches; twenty-three lines, extensively revised. Bound in an octavo volume, half brown morocco. Apparently a criticism of Burroughs' Notes on Walt Whitman, prepared by Whitman as a means of advertising himself in a newspaper or magazine (Camden Edition, vi, 23)-
      - "Feb. 25th '57 Dined with Hector Tyndale" (Volume 124)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; twenty-four lines. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. Criticisms of Leaves of Grass made by Whitman's friends, followed by a reminder to himself to use "American things, idioms... vegetables, animals'' (Camden Edition, vi, 154-155).
      - "for criticism L of Grass" (Volume 105)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 7x4 inches. Recto: twenty-seven lines, revised in red and black ink. Verso: Whitman has written out two stanzas from Tennyson's "The May Queen." Bound in a duodecimo volume, half green morocco. A passage of self-criticism, including material very similar to that in number 36, page 49 (Camden Edition, vi, 28-29).
      - "for Dr B's Criticism" (Volume 106)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on two sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches, one side only; forty-four lines, extensively revised. Bound in a duodecimo volume, half brown morocco. A statement of the purpose of Specimen Days.
      - "Friday April 24, '57. True vista before" (Volume 125)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of brown paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; twenty-seven lines. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, brown morocco back. Notes on the place and duties of the "public teacher," written apparently under the belief that his message would be delivered through orations (Camden Edition, vi, 7-8).
      - "Leading Characteristic" "The Great Construction —of the New Bible" (Box 20)
        Description from Frey: Two autograph manuscripts, written in pencil on two scraps of paper, about 2x4 inches, one side only; seven lines and six lines. Mounted and framed with a portrait of Whitman. A jotting on Whitman's purpose to unite all sects and parties, and a resolution to adhere to his "main life work—the Three Hundred & Sixty five," dated "June '57" (Camden Edition, vi, 6).
      - "Make the Works" "Boldness—Nonchalant ease indifference" (Volume 204)
        Description from Frey: Two autograph manuscripts, written in pencil on two scraps of paper, about 4x5 and 2x5 inches, one side only; nine lines and six lines. Mounted and framed with an autographed por trait of Whitman. Two bits of advice to himself on methods to be pursued in writing (Camden Edition, vi, 7).
      - "May 13 to 26 '8 1 Down in the country" (Volume 107)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of ruled paper, about 5x3 inches, one side only; forty-one lines. Bound in a duodecimo volume, full undyed morocco, gilt and blind tooled. A diary entry dealing with the period when Whitman was arranging and revising the copy for the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass (Diary in Canada, page 58).
      - "My Poems, when complete, should be A Unity" (Volume 126)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side only of two sheets of blue paper, about 8x5 inches; forty-six lines. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, blue morocco back. Notes intended as reminders of his aims and methods in writing his poems (Camden Edition, vi, 3, 8-9). A clipping headed "The Unity of the Bible" is pasted on the first page.
      - "No I do not choose to write a poem on a lady's sparrow" (Volume 134)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of blue paper, about 8x7 inches, one side only; twenty-one lines, revised in ink and pencil. A fragment in which Whitman declares his purpose to celebrate the chief themes employed in Leaves of Grass (Camden Edition, vi, 11-12).
      - "No one of the Themes generally considered fit for stock or motif" (Volume 114)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on one side only of nine sheets of paper, about 5x4 inches; 140 lines, written in ink and pencil, with numerous revisions. Bound in a duodecimo volume, cloth, green morocco back. A draft of an essay explaining the nature of Leaves of Grass (Camden Edition, vi, 20-22). With a note by W. S. Kennedy: "On L. of G., (written summer of 1871 in Washington)— W.S.K."
      - "Of William Blake Walt Whitman" (Box 20)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on two sheets of ruled paper, about 9x7 inches, one side only; thirty lines, revised in blue pencil. A brief critique comparing Blake and Whitman.
      - "On the other side is the 'barbaric yawp' of a very different poet" (Volume 206)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 3x7 inches; eleven lines, revised. Mounted and framed with a portrait. Part of an essay or critique arguing Whitman's difference from other poets (Camden Edition, vi, 191).
      - "(?) Other poets have formed for themselves an ideal" (Volume 115)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side only of two sheets of pink paper, about 8x5 inches; twenty-eight lines, revised. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. Fragments intended as suggestions for a preface or self-criticism (Camden Edition, vi, 31-32).
      - "Put in a passage in some poem to the effect of denounc'g" (Volume 199)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one piece of green paper, about 3x6 inches, one side only; seven lines. Mounted and framed with a portrait. A suggestion to himself to write a poetical passage denouncing those who translate his poems into foreign tongues with "increase or diminution" (Camden Edition, vi, 6).
      - "Rules for Composition" (Volume 136)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 10 x 8 inches, one side only; twenty-five lines, revised. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, green morocco back. Injunctions formulated by Whitman to guide his own practice in writing (Camden Edition, vi, 34-35).
      - "Sept '81 Copy of Leaves of Grass" "NY Mott Haven Nov 3 '81" (Volume 137)
        Description from Frey: Two autograph manuscripts, written on two sheets of ruled paper, 7x5 and 6x4 inches, one side only; seventeen lines in ink, eighteen lines written in pencil and revised in ink. Mounted in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Notes to remind the poet of certain details connected with the publication of the 1881-1882 edition of Leaves of Grass, and a diary note made in a railroad station on the way back to Camden after a three months' absence. With two newspaper clippings, dealing with Whitman's visit to Boston and the 1881-1882 edition, both annotated by the poet.
      - "Two suggestion points for letter" (Volume 205)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written and revised in ink on one sheet of paper, about 7x8 inches, one side only; twenty-two lines. The title is scrawled in blue pencil, in Whitman's hand, and was apparently added later. Mounted and framed with a photograph of Whitman. Two passages of self-criticism, the first closely related tonumber 19, page 45.
      - "? a T[ for Specimen Days" "2d vol Specimen Days" "Specimn Days 2d Vol" (Volume 116)
        Description from Frey: Three autograph manuscripts, written on three sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches, one side only; fifty-seven lines in all. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Reflections on nature, a comment on the "jumble" in Specimen Days, and a draft of part of a preface for the volume (Diary in Canada, pages 70-71).
    - Miscellany
      - The Black (The problem of the black) (Volume 192)
        Description from Frey: Manuscript, written in black ink on one side only, about 47 x 38 cm. Title written in red ink at bottom of page. In folder.
      - "Book-learn' g is good—let none dispense with it" (Volume 52)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; twenty-nine lines. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, orange morocco back. A fragment on the value of education as a help to personal qualities (Camden Edition, vi, 9-10).
      - "Caution" (Volume 196)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one piece of ruled paper, about 2x7 inches. Recto: nine lines, revised. Verso: a badly mutilated prose fragment. Mounted and framed with a portrait of Whitman. A reminder to the poet on the best way to "promulge" native American literature (Camden Edition, vi, 30).
      - "Egypt, (and probably much of the sentiment of the Assyrian empire)" (Volume 96)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side only of three sheets of paper, about 8x3 inches, and one small scrap; about eighty lines, revised. Bound in an octavo volume, half undyed morocco. Notes on the phases in the development of man represented by the Egyptians, Hindus, Greeks, Romans, and Hebrews (Camden Edition, vi, 103-104).
      - "Egyptian religion.... Greek.... Hebrew" (Volume 97)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of pink paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; about twenty-five lines, revised in pencil. In a board folder. A summary of what Whitman believed to be the essential ideas of the religions of the Egyptians, the Greeks, and the Hebrews (Camden Edition, vi, SS).
      - "The English Masses" (Volume 98)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on three sheets of blue paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; sixty-nine lines, revised. Bound in an octavo volume, half brown morocco. Impressions of the English common people, for the most part uncomplimentary, but ending with a panegyric on the power, pride, and individualism of England (Camden Edition, vi, 58-59).
      - "His idea of God (as in the oversoul) is beautiful" (Volume 34)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on a sheet of ruled paper, 10 x 8 inches, one side only; twenty-seven lines, revised. Comments on Emerson. At the top of the sheet appears an autograph endorsement by J. H. Johnston: "This page of Walt Whitman's MSS was given to me by his House Keeper after his death and presented by me to Homer Davenport with my Whitmanic regards. J. H. Johnston May 20 /09."
      - "I know well enough that man grows up, becom'g not a physical being merely" (Volume 53)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on one sheet of paper, about 11x6 inches, one side only; thirty lines, revised. Bound in a small narrow folio volume, boards. Comments on the nature of man (Camden Edition, vi, 148).
      - "In metaphysical points, here is what I guess about pure and positive truths" (Volume 67)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on one sheet of ruled paper, about 9x8 inches, one side only; twenty-six lines, much revised. Bound in a quarto volume, boards. A fragment giving Whitman's views on romantic inspiration and the shortcomings of professors, authors, and teachers (Camden Edition, vi, 142-143).
      - "It is generally believed in Washington that the President is in favor of a general exchange" (Volume 55)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on two sheets of paper, about 6x6 inches. Recto: thirty-three lines, written and revised in ink. Verso: "day and night monotonous —same th'g day after day"; thirty-nine lines, in pencil. Bound in a small quarto volume, half blue morocco. Rough drafts of material intended for a letter demanding more speed in the exchange of Civil War prisoners, with notes on the activities of various soldiers and a commentary on army hospitals.
      - "It were unworthy a live man to pray or complain" (Volume 203)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written and revised in pencil on a scrap of ruled paper, about 3x8 inches; six lines. Mounted and framed with a photograph of Whitman. A prose fragment on the ignobility of whining about "sin and hell" (Camden Edition, vi, 139-140).
      - "London— 1880 Then about drinking habits" (Volume 118)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on nine half-sheets of the stationery of the Asylum for the Insane, London, Ontario, about 8x5 inches, one side only; about 150 lines. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Notes on Whitman's impressions of Canada, made during his trip in 1880.
      - "A main part of The greatness of a humanity" (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of blue paper, about 7x4 inches, one side only; nineteen lines, revised in pencil and ink. Mounted and framed with a portrait of Whitman. A prose comment on the evolution of humanity (Camden Edition, vi, 70), followed by two verses suggested by the prose passage (iii, 259).
      - "Of Insanity" (Volume 87)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of green paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; thirty-five lines. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. Psychological jottings, on insanity and the four temperaments. A clipping discussing forcefulness in human personality {Life Illustrated, n.s., ii (May 31, 1856), 33) is mounted on the verso. Whitman has underlined several passages and made one annotation: "all about a locomotive."
      - Notes on Asia and Africa (Volume 224)
        Description from Frey: Nine autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on nine pieces of paper, of various sizes, one side only; about 175 lines in all. Mounted in a small folio volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Headings: "(Independent & Chinese) Tartary" (Camden Edition, vi, 216); "British in China" (vi, 59); "Russian serfs" (vi, 216); "Africa" (vi, 219-220); "Africa" (vi, 219); "Scythia" (vi, 53-54); "Bunsen The native name of Egypt is Khamiy (black,)" (vi, 51-52); "resume —(from Bunsen)" (vi, 52); "Oct. 1856 (London News. Illustrated, Sept. 27." Notes on Asia and Africa, taken down from conversations with travellers and from books of geography and history.
      - On Poetry (Volume 68)
        Description from Frey: Five autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on five scraps of paper, of various sizes; about fifty-five lines in all. Mounted in a small quarto volume, cloth, blue morocco back. Headings: "The greatest poems may not be immediately fully understood by outsiders" (Camden Edition, vi, 10-11); "The Poetry of other lands lies in the past" (vii, 28); "Health does not tell any more in the body, than it tells in literature" (vi, 158); "you cannot define too clearly what it is you love in a poem" (vi, 158); "Thought Of recognition" (iii, 271). A fragment of manuscript appears on the verso of the first piece.
      - "Produce great persons and the producers of great persons" (Volume 51)